hello welcome to active bookstream
number 1.2
it's February 15 2023.
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that's communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is recorded in archived live stream
so please provide us with feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will be following video
etiquette for live streams
check out
activeinference.org to get involved with
live streams and other projects
blue to you
great well this is our second discussion
of the book governing continuous
transformation we are here with the
author Bijan kazri today and we will be
discussing part two of the textbook
so I think we want to maybe go around
and introduce ourselves I am blue Knight
and independent research consultant in
New Mexico and I will pass it off to
Tyler
my name is Tyler I'm a protocol designer
and DOW researcher in California I said
to Daniel
I'm a researcher in California and pass
it to be Jean
okay so
um obviously an author uh really coming
much more from the Practical side of the
world having been serving on the boards
and eventually taking a strong interest
in the theory and being inspired by
active inference and in particular the
free energy minimization
principle to adopt that and apply it to
the world of corporate governance so
hence the book I very much appreciate
that you invited me today uh and
hopefully being in a having another
stimulating discussion I always love to
see how
um you know there's so much work which
goes into writing a book it's a very
lonely journey and when it's ones out
and you see actually such a gifted group
of people looking at it reading it
critically reviewing it and engaging in
a dialogue it's a great gift for an
authors so I'm I'm very very happy to be
here thank you
awesome well
Carry It Forward blue
so we are here um discussing part two of
free energy governance so over the last
four weeks we have discussed these last
four chapters
um and so today's discussion is going to
just Encompass those sections
so a bit of a road map we um had some
kind of category questions uh regarding
the role of empathy and free energy
governance the role of artificial
intelligence in free energy governance
and also on Duality management
um so starting off with empathy we got
here
um so I just actually was I think
looking up a photo for for like top down
bottom up like what does that look like
top down bottom-up organization
um and communication and and so like in
my photo scrolling I found this this old
paper right so it's from 2008
um and and it's about
um it's really about empathy and
emotional uh resonance so so
um this picture I thought was a great
picture and it had perception action
coupling and shared representation and
kind of like the self and other
distinction and I don't know John if
you've read this paper but but for me
like it was a figure that kind of
encompassed all these things that we've
been talking about in the book all along
um and so uh to quote bijan's book uh he
says cognition in the form of world
enactment is the purpose-directed
action-centric and social construction
of shared meaning and shared
expectations anchored in the
understanding that a firm's environment
is a matter of environmental engagement
in the form of interaction revealing
significance and assigning probabilities
to a bounded set of external unknown
States
and and I just was wondering like about
maybe the role of empathy in like
gaining a shared representation or a
shared
um understanding so I don't know if you
want to flip to the next there we go
um and so like here is empathy required
for this shared meaning and shared
expectations and I'm curious to know um
Bijan what your thoughts are maybe on on
either this or maybe I know we hear also
a lot about uh the role of emotional
intelligence in business success and so
where does maybe emotional intelligence
come into free energy governance like it
is that
um also essential or what are your
thoughts Theory okay now I think it's a
very good question first of all I did
not come across the paper I think it is
a brilliant uh illustration having said
so it's interesting to see it puts
perception and then action I put it the
other way around I see the action is
really determining our our perceptions
but I um
I I think it's a very very good question
because what you're doing is you're
opening something which I think as part
of my work I consider the Black Box
because when you look at
you know I don't like really bottom I
think I said this in one of our previous
discussions I prefer Frontline workers I
mean people are really in the front line
having said this the the top down
bottom-up Dynamic you have at every
hierarchical level and effectively
sometimes it's a question of how you
literally work together so then you open
up the black box of teamwork of
um how do you how do you engage actually
which is how do you understand each
other and I think that's where empathy
plays a very important role I think
that's where
um in emotional intelligence starts
playing a very important role what I
have done
for the purposes of the book for the
purposes of the free energy governance
concept I really focused on I think
communication
but there is a lot in communication
which is also empathy related You could
argue
um to make sure that actually
people hear what you're saying uh and
and obviously sometimes there needs to
be an empathetic dimension in it but
what I I think the
that the waterfall here is
you start really with a purpose when you
don't have a purpose then it becomes a
little bit fuzzy but if the purpose is
very clear that we want to go to Rome
then there's many ways that are leading
to wrong but as you're going on this
journey and keeping actually the team
together keeping the team energized
motivated of going through a lot of
Hazards maybe crossing the Alps from
from Europe uh to you to on the way to
Rome
um communication becomes very essential
and when you look at the Practical side
of the work even when you take a
publication like have a business review
which in my view is one really of the
leading business Publications which
addresses really current issues managers
company leaders but including Frontline
workers are focusing on and you see that
empathy emotional intelligence and
communication are really critical things
in making the most complex strategies
work because there is no point
um of being very smart about analyzing
where the world is going if you're not
able to align and motivate all the
resources all the dots of intelligence
in The Firm to join this so I stayed
away as part of the work of looking now
into the
microcosm of communication of what's
happening between
you know let's say a leader and a
Frontline worker how much empathy you
show in certain situations to ensure
that actually the whole flow is going to
work so I think to answer to summarize
the answer when you look at emotional
intelligence when you look at empathy
there are dimensions you would consider
more on a micro level in the way things
are being translated which I stayed away
from and really considered it as a black
box of how
the how probably
the communication is best done in very
specific circumstances
so that's clear because it's a it's a
very unusual I think it's a very good
question because it's a question which
really strikes the heart of management
um and has become obviously in recent
years a very popular theme
um
and nobody has ever asked me that
question in this context so I really
appreciate it
and I do remember um
I'm not sure if you've read
France that was like one of the very
first papers that we did at the
institute in our live streams but you
know it still is communication as like a
necessary tool and how communication is
used to kind of establish that that
shared meaning and shared expectation
um but as for like the nuts and bolts of
it it's still
um oh and then we didn't we did another
recent paper dealing with communication
as active inference kind of like the
follow-up but by a different author like
the Counterpoint to that paper I can't
remember the name of it um that was an
interesting thing I would really
appreciate if you could send me the
links to those papers sure sure
um Daniel I'm sure remembers and I can
go back through the live streams if uh I
don't remember
um I appreciate it thank you
um and so just do you think that
um
in human cognition we have we have
empathy in in human cognition and it
plays a role do you think that there's
an analog in organizational cognition
like do you think when a firm has
cognition that there's what would be
what would take like the equivalent role
of empathy in a firm if if anything or
or maybe that's kind of esoteric or what
what are your thoughts there
no I do think um
you know I mean what what is a firm a
firm is a legal fiction and it's it's
really a bunch of people and a bunch of
assets
and sometimes actually the only as it
could be the people let's say in a
Services business where there's no
Machinery or anything so
um I think it really comes down to
people I think it comes down to
leadership
it comes down to the identity it comes
down to the culture and in recent years
you've seen that many many companies I
mean through their leaders have paid a
lot of lip service to being an
empathetic organization having
understanding for the needs of the
workers um of the front liners of the
asset really of the company so I do
think that today
I cannot imagine that a firm which is
not empathetic and or or integrates
empathy
as a as an important pillar
of the values and the culture
it lives it doesn't have a great chance
to survive and when you look at at
culture what is culture in a corporate
in an organizational setting it's really
behavioral benchmarks which determine
really what we would expect of people in
this particular setting you know and uh
um and and I and I think this uh uh
empathy today is incredibly important
and by the way I do think that the
concept of empathy
has gained an entirely new dimension
following the pandemic you know when you
start seeing um people being locked up
having to when you have two working
parents kids sitting at home all of a
sudden there's so many things to juggle
where a company an employer needs to
show empathy and understanding for the
very particular challenges people face
and if you don't
um you you will eventually lose
sometimes even the best of your people
so another follow-up question on that
and maybe just to pose the question in a
slightly different way so a lot so far
we've been talking about empathy in
terms of like an individual human
cognition right and like hey that should
be an important part of your culture
because it allows communication to flow
within and without the form the firm
but I'm curious if there's an analog on
the The Firm organizational level scale
so in the same way that on an individual
scale you're mirroring the Motions of
another person of an external
um individual is there a way in which
the organization as its own entity
mirrors the outside world and mirrors
kind of its own perception of the
environment and what you could call the
emotions of other firms or other
processes happening in this external
environment it's a very like maybe
strange question but I'm kind of curious
in what way do you think that the firm
under free energy governance is
receptive
and can integrate information in this
external environment uh and is that a
different in a way to how people
traditionally think of like Gathering
data about the environment
well when you look at actually if you
were to dissect empathy and what is it
really I think there's two
this two two three dimensions I could
instantly think of you you a you say
a person matters so somebody matters
secondly you respect that person
and certainly you really
um you listen I think the listening part
is an incredibly important part how can
you be empathetic if you haven't
listened in the first place so when you
look at all these three dimensions
respect
listening
um
the idea that some some somebody and
what somebody has to say matters is
an essential Foundation of free energy
governance because free energy
governance effectively says even the
weak signals bear the transformative
potential we need to listen to so first
of all you need to open all your senses
in free energy governance
to listen to what actually frontliners
have to say
and
start was the working assumption that
what they have to say matters
doesn't matter what in in what area uh
they address it
um to be able to read in between the
lines so that's the only way I could
stretch the the concept the dimension of
empathy and really link it into
um into free energy governance by
dissecting it into let's say these three
dimensions what empathy stands for and
then pull it back into the free energy
governance framework which effectively
says
the
strategy fundamentally is a generative
process
of prediction error minimization
and so you may articulate predictions at
the top but they are only as good as you
can challenge them with bottom-up data
and the bottom-up data to access it to
make it
flow from the bottom to the top probably
requires an element of empathy because
my personal experience is the more you
go the closer you go to the front lines
in an organization
the stronger is actually the resistance
to sharing valuable information
and the reason it's not that people
don't want to share
the reason is that people prefer not to
stick out
people prefer not necessarily to assume
responsibility now for for something
they say or even if it becomes a project
in its own right that they may have to
execute but they wouldn't want to
execute it so what you find is unlocking
the valuable intelligence which is at
the front lines of an organization
is a management challenge in its own
right and I think it requires very
strong communication and it certainly
requires empathy and the empathy and
maybe now I can I can close the circle
here to your question Tyler and what
blue was referring to before
maybe it has to be more
than just an empathetic leader maybe it
has to be trust in processes in an
entire culture that I feel comfortable
about for this to work on a continuous
and sustainable basis because when we
look at free energy governance this is
not like a one-off project this is
ingrained into the DNA of the firm of
saying the future of the firm is best
ascertained if we continuously
generatively minimizing prediction error
so predictions at the top but possibly
sometimes at the bottom and we want to
challenge those predictions with
Frontline intelligence
so um just a quick follow-up as you were
um talking about especially about like
the pandemic and I was there like
thinking about
empathy and Leadership
um you know I was just directed back to
the task positive Network versus the
direct default default mode Network and
and so I think maybe like empathy is is
the central
um component in the default mode Network
like empathy like the default mode
network is like the people-centered part
of that
um and and I was I think like now with
the pandemic like it just like Jarred me
into like we're now so I feel like we're
so off task like I mean maybe not in
every organization but I think as a
society like we're so much more centered
we're flipped into heavy on the DMM um
as opposed to the tpn uh just just
culturally because of the the greater
amount of empathy that everyone was just
required to drum up for um people and
and
um their circumstances right
and I do think what has reinforced it's
it's a very good way of looking actually
at the um task specific uh uh uh Network
or in the default mode Network you're
absolutely right the empathy is part of
the default mode when you look now at
the pandemic
it was all about the default mode I mean
because there was so much misery so much
tragedy certainly in the first waves and
the uncertainty and predictability in
our models were overwhelmed because our
world models were not prepared to deal
with this it took a year a year and a
half and we integrated the pandemic
perfectly well into an adjusted a
further evolved model and we developed
new strategies of how to deal with this
but one element is for example home
office and when you think about how hard
it has become for many firms to bring
people back to the office and you could
almost say the office is Maybe
the physical representation of the
task-specific network
you know you go because you're really
executing a specific task in in a
building and then you leave it and then
you know you're out of it so almost
there was a there was a certain Link in
the brain between office
and task specificity
um I do recall another example which is
kind of interesting in that context but
I don't want to drift up too far but I
do recall that Banks introduced
um
you know it was kind of only in the 90s
I think that they introduced that you
can have a casual Friday
so normally it was really just you wear
a suit and then you come on Fridays you
can wear casual smart
and I remember somebody was telling me
actually uh when you go on the Goldman
Sachs trading floor the person who has a
hole in the sweater and all of this on a
Friday that's probably the guy who makes
most the money because he shows like I
don't even have to wear this Market but
a lot of people said when the financial
crisis hit in 2008 and which was really
exuberance of you know all that cheap
money putting a lot of people into
misery uh was was that and and mortgages
that this was partly related to the fact
that
the Casual Friday became almost the
Casual the whole week and it had an
impact on on how uh people were
performing actually their tasks and
their their attitude towards risk so I
do think that form and informality are
very very critical aspects of of you
know how an organization works and
sometimes the informal organization
which is obviously a function of the
formal one
can be much more important and sometimes
it can be much more important how
information is Flowing most of the time
in organizations coming back to the free
energy governance framework
the most valuable information does not
come
through the formal channels it comes
through informal channels it may come
through a conversation at the water
cooler
all these things which are not
necessarily documented in the
traditional forms of corporate
communication so I think these are
probably also the channels where empathy
can be best
communicated and I think the big loss of
um during the pandemic was that while
the the office work and the office space
was maybe very formal and very
um
tasks specific
I think it was at the same time
underestimated how important it is to
provide to frontliners to even to
leaders the source of empathy in
exchange because I think most people
were confronted with the terrible
loneliness and so we shouldn't
underestimate and we shouldn't
Bash Too Much the physical office space
is a very important place not only where
um uh where you perform your task but
could be also a source of of being
energized and receiving understanding
for issues which have nothing to do with
your job and more importantly it's
really the the side of learning I do
recall when Morgan Stanley CEO insisted
that people are coming back to the
office it was really by saying our
future as a company is dependent on
continuing training people and bringing
in young Talent who have to learn on the
job how can they learn on the job when
the office is empty so there is a duty
in the name of firm survival to keep the
firm as a learning side and that means
bringing in the side so that's a long
talk
um obviously the the concept of empathy
in the context of free energy governance
it's not an obvious one but I think this
is an interesting very interesting
conversation and I do think that we um
we need to dissect
the what really empathy means for and
then we need to look at what is a firm a
firm consisting of people of assets but
also of the physical space and I think
the space is a is a very important
Dimension to consider uh and that's
where the pandemic is an interesting
example of how it can be a source of
um of
whatever positive we associate was
empathy to provide
awesome so we'll move now into talking a
little bit more about artificial
intelligence
um and do you say in the book you say in
fact we are challenged not to allow for
the human brain's computational limits
to solely determine perception and sense
making instead Outsourcing some of the
heavy information lifting to the
environment in form of extended
cognition is the essence of optimizing
prediction error minimization the more
exponential and hence discontinuous a
market environment the more we need
self-organizing mechanisms that leverage
the world as a supervisory signal
challenging and circular causality the
very perceptual content of our
predictions
and in reading this I have been having
lots of fun working with GPT chat as I'm
sure you have and many others have have
been um and really as as just kind of a
like a platform or a standing like a
springboard for like where we what we
already know like it's a very big
cognitive synthesis of like you know the
whole internet Circa 2021 or or
something like that and so like this is
really a cognitive extension like our
smartphone and many other things uh um
and so I just was wondering what role
you might see for chat GPT or other
automated artificial intelligence I mean
like the you know there's no limit to
um assist us with free energy governance
because I really see like an assisting
with the synthesis and integration of
information like at a very large scale
even just now compared to a year ago so
do you see a role um for AI in free
energy governance or helping us to kind
of
springboard our leadership platforms
yeah
very good question so let me
um uh there's many dimensions to it
number one
um
free energy governance
strictly speaking
that's not consider making use of AI at
the board level
now when you look and let's briefly talk
about an organization applications of AI
you have today
I mean so many examples from credit
cards where you have ai I mean which
used to be which has been now automated
in in a massive way of how credit checks
are happening on the spot it's no longer
left to the retailer but there's a
central system which can authorize the
credit card transaction instantly or
refuse it so there has been predictive
algorithms
um being centralized and changing
the way certain tasks have been done in
an organization so I would say the
application of AI today is very much at
the front lines where it's probably
a little bit further up the chain also
is if you look at Healthcare so a
radiologist
is possibly redundant today but if you
make the radiologist redundant because a
machine can maybe possibly read
uh the image is much better it may have
repercussions of how you're going to
start organizing the whole hospital
because who's assuming now what role and
maybe the role of the nurse is going to
be upskilled because on the basis of the
machine output uh there will be
direction to the right doctor to to look
really for treatment whatever is the
reading from um from the images so I
think we need to
um
see now that AI starts first of all in a
very task specific way
but moves up and all of a sudden has
very systemic changes applying a i
at the board level
um
I don't see this
at this moment you know information
processing
will not be done at the board level with
AI tools I I doubt this at this point
when I look now specifically at free
energy governance well free energy
governance if you look at free energy
principle for me that is an artificial
active inference and the way uh
carliferson has been even applying it to
neuroimaging is a machine learning
algorithm so for me free energy
governance
is really a machine learning logic
in its entirety now when you look at
what is happening uh chat GPT is not as
smart as a lot of people think at the
end it's just a language model and uh it
it makes statistically very plausible
language it produces which it doesn't
understand itself so it poses obviously
great challenges so I think that has
been a little bit misleading having said
this
I think it's not misleading to the
extent that chat GPT is an indication
that generative intelligence automated
augmented is the future and this is
going to come and I think we will have a
hard time and humans to catch up how
fast it can evolve and the things it's
doing because it's getting better every
day because it's training on the back of
massive training knowledge now
what is happening
and that is definitely a challenge for
the board you could ask how can the
board continue fulfilling its most basic
fiduciary duty of monitoring company and
management if itself the board has no
means of understanding what the
algorithms do because algorithms can be
potentially very damaging so I do see
that there will be a safety and ethical
um a regulatory Dimension which will
probably need to be addressed at the
board level when you look at it from an
AI point of view now so that's a little
bit to the question of artificial
intelligence and free energy governance
I specific specifically have not
considered any tools at the board level
now when you look at what is artificial
intelligence really about it allows you
to separate two components which make up
a decision it's a predictive component
and it's a judgment component I think
the predictive component can be more and
more done the prediction element by
machines on the back of data but I do
think that it revalues the Judgment
component of the human
now it could be that
it's no longer really the top let's say
leaders which are best positioned to
make the Judgment component maybe people
on the front lines
now being empowered by artificially
intelligence fueled prediction models
and prediction tools can place a much
better position to make the right
judgment call so I think the impact of
artificial intelligence on the company
will be more distributed decision making
to be really more in real time
now coming back to the quote you
originally were reading out
the the most important element of that
quote is
what you see today
is that most people in leadership
positions will tell you the world has
become uncertain and it's unpredictable
and my answer to this is always first of
all uncertainty and unpredictability is
a very subjective concept it's not an
objective reality
and
your perception of uncertainty or
unpredictability is really a function of
how good is your world model how good is
your prediction model so if you're
telling me the world is uncertain you're
effectively telling me your model is not
good enough
of modeling it and in a generative
actively inferential way going step by
step forward to improve it and make the
world less uncertain
by the way I do believe also for the
pandemic was a brilliant example if you
if you had a world model which maybe
Bill Gates had that pandemics are going
to come they're going to be massive and
they're going to be Global there's no
way you're going to contain in today's
world something which started in China
it's going to stay in Wuhan but it's
going to be Global but if you think
about it it started off in 2019 November
December and people until January
February in the Western Hemisphere still
thought this was a Chinese problem
and they weren't prepared at all now
think about it some people were smart
enough and they exploited the business
opportunity by going up front into
producing a massive amount of face masks
so when all of a sudden the pandemic hit
in March April they were the ones making
fortunes because governments didn't have
the right prediction model and they
didn't have enough masks I know actually
the guys who did take advantage of this
in Switzerland and I think they made 250
million dollars or something like this
and they they because they caught really
the government naked so you see the
discrepancy even governments where you
suppose was all the resources they have
at hand all the information they have
they have bad prediction models so
your prediction model determines
how uncertain and how unpredictable the
world is
and a big problem you have today in
companies is that companies do not
Embrace uncertainty but they bury
uncertainty a book which puts this
brilliantly into perspective is from
agaval and Avi Fab
um It's called Power and prediction and
it shows very clearly how companies have
developed as aguiri said uh back in the
60s it's skilled incompetence where you
act in a way which is really contrary to
your intentions or what you really want
to achieve and what has happened is that
companies have created rules best
practices
um you could even argue that putting the
CEO in a super dominant position
controlling everything
is a form of bearing uncertainty because
you look now to one person and you say
that person is going to give me all the
answers of the world instead what we
need to do is we need to make our models
available to testing in the marketplace
in a generative inferential way
by acting and generating new data points
that make our model in a generative
fashion better and better and as a
result of it our predictions models get
better the predictions they produce get
better and the world will be perceived
as less uncertain and that's really the
essence of the quote you started off
with
so we have two elements here one is
really the the uncertainty
um element I I think we need to really
highlight is a subjective concept and
it's a question of world modeling or
prediction modeling and prediction
testing the second uh Dimension you
addressed is the one of artificial
intelligence I do think artificial
intelligence or augmented intelligence
You could argue is it really that
artificial
um uh is is is is just at the very
beginning it's going to be exponential
it's going to be faster evolving and
spreading that anybody can expect and I
do believe that
in around within 10 years
70 to 80 percent of knowledge workers
will disappear and only those people
will survive working in any organization
that can understand manage and
complement
artificial intelligence
and by the way there's so many examples
you can see how artificial intelligence
allowed in an incredible way to get rid
of
I mean millions of jobs
you know
already
and even if you think about a
radiologist has a very uh intense
training in medical education
and in the book power prediction is a
really good example I think it is in
that book other there is another great
book I recommend on the topic it's all
in on AI by devonport and mittal which
gives you a really good overview good
structure a few good case studies and
you can see that the the the the the the
the job of a radiologist
can be divided into I think roughly 35
or 38 tasks and when you look at each of
the tasks a machine can do this today so
that job is gone
yeah it's interesting the level of
synthesis so so how much of our so for
me the essence of that quote was
um cognitive offloading into systems
that can synthesize and integrate
information
um how much of that task is what is done
by Ai and I do agree with you that we
will um need to be able to work with the
AI like to understand that synthesized
synthesis and integration of information
that's provided by augmented
intelligence systems in order to be
functional in the workplace going
forward
um yeah but you see the big weaknesses
where people don't understand by the way
that quote when I recall
um it's
it's Howie you guys know Howie he wrote
a brilliant book The predictive brain
and how he is probably more structural
Bayesian guy
um but he's really brilliant in the way
he shows
it actually would
the the Bayesian brain is about is
is really you you you you
you use the world as a feedback loop
so you you can come up with any
predictions you want let the world
you know give you all the feedback you
need and that's a that's a very powerful
way of how you start a general in a
generative way
reducing uncertainty
definitely so I don't know I guess we
should maybe go on to our last set of
questions on Duality management
um so here Bijan is it only critical for
the board to understand Duality
management or do you think at every
level of the hierarchy from the front
line workers up to top tier management
to end the board does everyone need to
understand Duality management and
practice this or is it only necessarily
at the top
well I I I don't think you would explain
to anyone in the front line that you
have to engage in Duality but
um because it's a certain degree it's an
abstract con concept and I developed
Duality management really at the at the
very very top level almost
you know dynamic capabilities the
concept of dynamic capabilities
in strategy management
is defined a dynamic capability as a
non-operational capability so you say
it's a some call it also a meta
capability so it's not a task specific
capability so you would almost say when
we talk about Duality management you
move very quickly into the default mode
side of the brain and what it really is
about I I used it in the context and I
think I I said it in our last discussion
you can really reduce
everything about a company about two
Dimensions one is exploiting today's
Cash Flow and making the money that's
really the business you have and
developing the future cash flow stream
which is the exploration so you have
exploitation exploration and
there have been so many theories about
and and case studies about can you do
both at the same time how does it work
and sometimes people said oh you do
exploitation here but you create a whole
different new thing over there and you
don't mix them and sometimes they don't
mix that easily I don't think companies
have that luxury any longer and I think
exploitation focusing on today's Cash
Flow and doing something new is it
really that radical is it more
incremental is happening kind of in real
time
but it requires very strong leadership
because when you think about exploiting
today's Cash Flow is a very hardcore
operational activity so CEOs usually
immerse very very strongly in the
exploitative activity when they're
really good they can also do exploration
and they need to make sure how they
switch between the default mode which is
probably more for exploration thinking
creatively about Innovation projects and
at the same time managing
and optimizing an existing cash
generating business
my idea was
um behind Duality management to say
the board
has is actually uniquely positioned
because it's not involved in any
operational activities really of the
company the board is not involved in
running today's business
it can have a great super View
of saying where should actually maybe
the CEO be guided towards of maybe
emphasizing right now more exploitation
or exploration where people see as a
board when they analyze the business
they can see the problems that concerns
one complex second complex I have is
financial and strategic
um control and they really stand for
in-house Innovation and Innovation you
buy through by buying other companies or
certain things and
um I the view of the free and or the way
free energy governance
um
and this is how the whole section 2 is
structured you have the structural
component which is really how you
connect the top at the bottom the
cognition component is really related to
how you have a an ability to an accurate
World create a model and I always like
the Googles the Facebooks all these
companies who have created massive
businesses but they really created this
um in in a in an active way they did not
copy someone they did not do a market
research or adapt but they had a vision
of their own which I think is essential
and the third dimension are the
capabilities and the capabilities I
developed this Duality management as a
dynamic capability and dynamic
capability is really a specific meta
capability in strategy management so I
think when you look at these two
complexes how much do I focus on the
business I have how much do I focus on
the business I would like to have
tomorrow and how much of it is done
in-house and how much of this is done
possibly by buying it uh
uh forces which sometimes uh uh uh are
going against or going in line and I
think the board in its meta position
supervisory position being above the
executive leadership has a unique
position to practice this so that
indirectly answers your question I think
Duality management the more you go down
in the hierarchy of a business which
means the closer you go to the front
lines where heart tasks are being
performed the less you have a duality
management you shouldn't have a duality
management at all because people are
really focused on very specific tasks
and the further you move up and the more
you have to decide are you going to do
one of this or more of this you may find
The Duality management challenge so it
may not be just on the board but it's
certainly on the board when it comes to
exploitation exploration and financial
and strategic control
now that's a long answer I gave I hope
you could follow me
that's great thank you so much I try to
make it simple because obviously
um when you look at the very origins of
this book it was originally a
dissertation which started off uh really
in strategy management
uh and uh I'm so happy that I found it
all the way to the more neuroscientific
Dimension and we're talking the in the
in the context of the active inference
Institute
um but obviously when you talk
specifically about The Duality
management side we are really pretty
much in in Business Schools
so getting going from
um maybe a more uh
thoughtful to the more practical
um can you give an example of um
how you can reduce organizational
friction through this top-down bottom-up
hierarchical coupling like it gets very
fuzzy for me as I mean even as we're
talking about like what levels need to
understand Duality management like the
the I mean I get the communication
between the levels is key to like
organizational maintenance or like the
Persistence of a firm
um but but like Translating that into
some kind of practical terms that I
could apply at my firm for instance is
maybe a little bit more difficult so so
do you have
um any advice for us that are you know
down here in the nitty-gritty of it all
[Music]
um
so
I do think what tools you apply
that are practically of relevance is
maybe a function also of the size of the
organization so let's start with a
really big organization take a big
Insurance Company
and you have the board of an insurance
company which will be very respectable
people who have probably jobs as CEOs on
many different other companies they come
together four or five times a year they
take major decisions
um
how can such a board
better understand
independently of CEO framing as a filter
what overall is going on how can the
board make the CEO stronger to ensure
that the CEO actually is properly
connected with what's really going on
in in the in the in the in the front
lines and one concept I I like a lot I
think I've talked about it before but I
I think the concept
is a good concept to bring as an example
again because it highlights and then you
can think creatively of what other
things you can think of but they are
Shadow boards so having a group of young
high potential people who are quite far
removed from the very top
that they form aboard themselves and
have board meetings with very similar
agenda items and can discuss what should
be maybe the future agenda items and
that can serve as a tremendous source of
inspiration from the front lines to the
main board which is sitting on the very
top
and that is a wonderful way I see as
connecting uh the top and the bottom and
leading the information flow companies
which have done this is like total
energy one the French one of the biggest
energy companies in the fashion business
Prada Gucci
um and when you think about it Prada and
Gucci are obviously companies which are
living off young Talent people young
designers something edgy something new
uh because think about it in fashion
you've got to come up every season with
something which is setting a trend so
you're really dependent on being
connected to the front line and from
creative people picking up what is the
next so I like the fashion houses
because they show how important it is to
be connected to the very front lines a
big insurance company may not see it but
a big insurance company may be missing
what be the next
big thing maybe young people will be
asking for as a business model
for as an interesting Insurance market
and
um so I think that is a really good
two now let's go into small
organizations let's take the active
inference Institute as an example and
you're saying look we have this
wonderful scientific Advisory Board you
have uh a wonderful board who is
advising you uh uh and and and and and
and and guiding you
um how to make how to increase I mean
you have I think you have one purpose to
increase the impact of the active
Insurance Institute in the marketplace
and you're looking at various tools
you're looking at very various
engagement platforms our dialogue is one
of them you're reaching out through
channels to at every juncture optimize
that and I'm trying to support this as
well because I really truly believe in
in the mission of the active
interference Institute and I do believe
that it is the very beginning
of a great movement because I see that
as the future I'm absolutely convinced
of that so in that regard you're
definitely Pioneers our community is
still very small
now here's the question of how you
connect the top
which is you guys now was the was the
front line and the front line may have
really interesting
weak signals which could give you some
really inspirational input where you say
we should take it on and I think you're
doing it you're doing it with a
newsletter you're reaching out you're
obviously want to make sure people read
it they engage with this and you have
internship programs you have a number of
ways of how to bring in
really the the marketplace to challenge
you to improve you was one and only one
Mission and purpose in mind to make sure
that the products the output from the
active inference Institute has impact
represents the aspirations you have for
high quality intelligence
um that more and more people should
connect to and I think you're doing
quite a great job with the limited
resources you have by doing all these
tools creating these dialogues you are
acting actually to generate great
data points including our conversations
and the way you then package the outputs
to reach out and collect input from
people we may not know at this point who
may connect to the content and I think
this is a form
of structure in a very distributed
environment when you look at how the
active interference Institute is working
of connecting actually the top which is
you guys
the front lines are possibly people like
myself giving feedback so Frontline is
not always you know it doesn't imply is
somebody
um that's why I don't like the word
bottom
sometimes your most intelligent people
in the network may be your frontliners
giving you the right feedbacks and data
points I hope that's that answers the
question and puts a little bit more more
tangibly into your perspective
most definitely and I think uh thank you
for all the nice things you have to say
about the active inference Institute
that's always uh it's always nice to get
a compliment
um and I think that um that's it for
today unless there's any more like
burning thoughts or questions
foreign
I think the the next chapter goes a
little bit more into the corporate
governance side
I I think we've covered quite a bit uh
of this so when you I think uh next one
is three conclusion
um and um
I think 13 uh
uh chapter 13
um which is our performance and survival
as a matter of self-organization
is quite philosophical I think is a is a
topic and um
I look forward to it
and thank you so much for for also
taking interest in my work it means a
lot to an author
thank you we will see you next time okay
all the best
peace